# **Songlin Jiang**

✓ songlin.jiang@aalto.fi
 ♦ hollowman6.github.io
 • in songlin-jiang
 ✔ HollowM186
 • C HollowMan6
 • Last updated on November 8, 2023

My academic fervor converges with enhancing **computer systems**, **networks**, **databases**, and their corresponding **security** aspects, which allows my research to have impacts on computing for both the environment (**greener while efficient**) and people (**faster while reliable**). Additionally, I am a passionate **free software advocate**. During my leisure time, I maintain several open-source projects and contribute to many others.

#### **Education**

2022 – 2024
2023 – 2024
Spring 2020
2018 – 2022

### **Experience**

Developer Relations Engineer, Enclaive (confidential computing, with Prof. Sebastian Gajek) 06/2023 - Present

- Technical **documentation**, tutorials and content creation
- O Channel management to interact with the community and grow the base

Coding Experience, *Igalia* (Wolvic, ex. Mozilla Firefox Reality)

06/2023 - Present

- OVR Browser Development, Android deprecated methods refactoring
- O Address user issues, UI and openXR related feature implementation

**HPC Developer Internship**, CSC - IT Center for Science

05/2023 - 08/2023

- O Develop the **GPU monitoring service** for HPC clusters (NVIDIA and AMD GPUs, including LUMI)
- O Develop the Documentation GPT chatbot service using IlamaIndex, LangChain and Redis
- o Make improvements to the HPC web operating interface project Open OnDemand in Ruby on Rails
- LUMI ranked 3rd around the world and 1st in Europe at HPC supercomputer TOP500 list by 2023

**CNCF LFX Mentorship**, *Kubescape* (Kubernetes security platform)

03/2023 - 05/2023

- Add packaging support for various package managers in Linux, macOS, and Windows
- Improve release CI by adding ARM64 binaries building and testing support (by QEMU and cross compiling),
   and also support Kubescape auto version bumping for other Kubescape-related repositories
- Enable Kubescape GitHub action to support code review based on generated SARIF report

Rhino-Bird Open-Source Training Program, Tencent (Kona JDK)

07/2022 - 09/2022

o Generate keypairs for SM2 by various algorithms with JDK library, compare performance and security

Google Summer of Code, MIT CSAIL & Google (Blockly, web-based visual program editor) 05/2022 - 09/2022

Allow selecting, dragging and manipulating multiple blocks for Google Blockly by creating a plugin

O Resolve the issue that had troubled the Google Engineers for a decade (since the Blockly project started) o @mit-app-inventor/blockly-plugin-workspace-multiselect now has average 50+ downloads per week **Summer of Bitcoin**, *Cryptoanarchy Debian* (Bitcoin related Debian packages) 05/2022 - 08/2022 Add Continuous Integration (CI) by investigating systemd support inside Docker with GitHub Actions O Chances to get into this internship in 2022: 83/20317 RL Open Source Fest, Microsoft Research NYC (Vowpal Wabbit, ML library) 05/2022 - 08/2022 $\circ$  Add native CSV parser support for the Vowpal Wabbit project in C++, 100% Test & Code Coverage • Finally managed to make 10x performance improvement and is comparable to VW text format Open Source Intern, Institute of Software, CAS (openEuler, Linux distribution) 01/2022 - 07/2022o First to obtain 150 intern credits. Help solve 6 issues, related technologies include D-Bus, Glib, building Cloud Native Container images, Rust programming, Chrome DevTools Protocol, test case, RPM packaging One of the achievement mdbook-pdf now has average 100+ downloads per week 06/2021 - 08/2021**Google Summer of Code**, *openSUSE* (IBus, input method framework) Add custom themes feature for IME framework IBus, improve IBus settings support in GNOME O A blog post at **openSUSE News** that introduces my work GNOME extension Customize IBus now has average 100+ downloads per week **OSPP Summer**, *openEuler* (Developed an ISO writer using QT and C++) 07/2021 - 09/2021**OSPP Summer**, Emacs Application Framework (EAF, work with Yong Wang) 07/2020 - 09/2020 Address issues using Emacs Lisp, Python, JavaScript, SQLite to add new features for Emacs Application A blog post (in Chinese) about my work posted by Yong Wang (ManateeLazyCat) Summer of Code, Alibaba (Arthas, Java diagnostic tool) 07/2020 - 08/2020 Write Chinese and English online tutorials for Arthas using Katacoda and Vue.js Highlight: Support directly searching Class Loader by name instead of Hash Code using Java

### Certificates & Honors & Awards

SECCLO Erasmus Mundus Scholarship (26/767) Full-ride scholarship, including tuition and living costs	2022 – 2024
Aalto University School of Science Dean's Incentive Scholarship	2023
Cloud Captains in Linux Foundation Training (LiFT) Scholarship (China)	2022
Huawei Cloud Certified Developer Associate in Internet of Things (HCCDA - IoT)	2022
Certified Kubernetes Administrator (CKA), CNCF	2022
Recognized Tencent Open Source Contributor Only 30+ were issued globally by then	2022
Intern of Excellence Award at <b>Tencent</b>	2022
2/4000+ to receive all the 3 kinds of intern awards Intern of Excellence & Star of Open Source Award in openEuler Open Source Internship	2022
Only 3/150+ interns received both awards  China Ministry of Education & Huawei "Intelligent Base" Future Star Scholarship	2021
Software Design Engineer, China Qualification of Computer and Software Professional	2021
Excellent Student Award in Baidu Software Engineering Training Camp	2021
Academic Aces in Linux Foundation Training (LiFT) Scholarship (China)	2020

CATTI Level 3 (English & Chinese) Translator	2020
Best Paper Award in Lanzhou University Summer Social Practice Report Paper: Research on the Functionality and Optimization of Urban Communities in China During COVID-19 in 2020 Award in openEuler University Developer Competition	2020 2020
Ranked 1st in final defense Star of Innovation Award in Alibaba T-head OCC Developers IoT Innovation Competition	2020
My proposal ranked 1st in voting (850 votes, 300 more than the 2nd one)  China Scholarship Council Outstanding Undergraduate International Exchange Scholarship  (Only 1) Full covering of visa fees, traveling fees, and living costs, plus the host university exchange program tuition fee waiver a Google InnoCamp Hangzhou BoostMakers — TensorFlow Boost	2019 agreement 2019
40+/2000+ Excellent Project Award in Lanzhou University Innovation and Entrepreneurship Plan	2019
Project: Renaissance – Al + Dunhuang Art, supervised by Prof. Qingguo Zhou	.8 - 2022 test fee
Open Source Repositories	
1.5k+ GitHub followers. 55.5k+ GitHub stars across all of the following selected repositories:	
1. kubescape/kubescape — ★9.1k — Kubernetes Security Platform	2023
Rank #9 among all contributors with 40 commits, 745 lines of additions and 555 lines of deletions 2. lgalia/wolvic — ★633 — Immersive VR Browser	2023
Rank #7 among all contributors with 117 commits, 8008 lines of additions and 3712 lines of deletions  3. VowpalWabbit/vowpal_wabbit — ★8.3k — Machine Learning System	2022
Rank #77 among all contributors with 3 commits, 1611 lines of additions and 83 lines of deletions 4. ThibaultJanBeyer/DragSelect — ★606 — DragSelect JavaScript UI Library	2022
Rank #6 among all contributors with 3 commits, 213 lines of additions and 23 lines of deletions  5. debian-cryptoanarchy/cryptoanarchy-deb-repo-builder — **137 — Bitcoin Packages for Debian	2022
Rank #4 among all contributors with 7 commits, 245 lines of additions and 22 lines of deletions	
6. HollowMan6/mdbook-pdf — ★106 — MdBook backend for PDF Generation Rank #1 among all contributors with 35 commits, 3152 lines of additions and 527 lines of deletions	2022
7. mit-cml/workspace-multiselect — ★5 — Blockly Multi-Select Plugin Rank #1 among all contributors with 18 commits, 11846 lines of additions and 20978 lines of deletions	2022
8. openSUSE/Customize-IBus — ★47 — Full Customization of IBus UI Rank #1 among all contributors with 354 commits, 42984 lines of additions and 30128 lines of deletions	2021
9. openSUSE/IBus-Theme-Hub — ★19 — IBus Themes CSS Rank #1 among all contributors with 21 commits, 3190 lines of additions and 442 lines of deletions	2021
10. openSUSE/IBus-Theme-Tools — ★13 — IBus Theme Generator	2021
Rank #1 among all contributors with 104 commits, 8558 lines of additions and 4654 lines of deletions 11. alibaba/arthas — ★33.7k — Java Diagnostic Tool	2020
Rank #2 among all contributors with 80 commits, 25191 lines of additions and 1543 lines of deletions  12. emacs-eaf/emacs-application-framework — ★2.8k — Emacs Application Framework	2020
Rank #5 among all contributors with 49 commits, 3482 lines of additions and 1033 lines of deletions  13. HollowMan6/TinyML-ESP32 — ★106 — TinyML Programs for ESP32	2020
Rank #1 among all contributors with 11 commits, 78393 lines of additions and 19530 lines of deletions	
Invited Talks	
Content, Link to the talk, and Date:	
<ol> <li>Virtual Network Systems among Containers, Aalto University Secure Systems Demo Day</li> <li>Multi-Select Plugin, Google Blockly Summit</li> </ol>	06/2023
3. Native CSV Parser, Microsoft Research NYC Seminar (RLOSFest)	06/2023 08/2022
4. Summary of my Open Source Internship, openEuler Excellent Intern Seminar	08/2022
5. Update Notification Program in Python, openEuler University Developer Competition	05/2021
6. Summary of my Contribution to Arthas, Alibaba Summer of Code Presentation	08/2020

## **Professional Activities**

openSUSE Member 2021 – Present

## **Software Copyright**

<ul> <li>Hollow Software for Smartly Memorizing Words</li> </ul>	CN 2020SR0839716
<ul> <li>Hollow Software System for Sport Center Management</li> </ul>	CN 2020SR0839709
Hollow Software for Jack Compiler	CN 2020SR0839702
<ul> <li>Hollow Software for Picture &amp; Video Information Hiding En-Decryption</li> </ul>	CN 2020SR0079950
Face Recognition Access Control System	CN 2019SR1388115

## Publications [Google Scholar, 2 citations with h-index of 1]

#### 2019

 Voting System Based on Wechat Pay Songlin Jiang

Computer Engineering & Software 2019

### **Skills**

Programming Go, Rust, Java, Kotlin, JavaScript, C++, C, Python, HTML, Shell, SQL ... Frameworks GitHub Actions, Flutter, React, Viper, Selenium, TensorFlow, scikit-learn ...

#### **Courses**

Some top-quality courses I've taken:

<ul> <li>Program Analysis, DTU</li> </ul>	Fall 2023
<ul> <li>Program Verification, DTU</li> </ul>	Fall 2023
<ul> <li>Programming Parallel Computers, Aalto University</li> </ul>	Spring 2023
<ul> <li>Platform Security, Aalto University</li> </ul>	Spring 2023
<ul> <li>Cloud Software and Systems, Aalto University</li> </ul>	Fall 2022
<ul> <li>Multimedia Services in Internet, Aalto University</li> </ul>	Fall 2022
<ul> <li>Designing and Building Scalable Web Applications, Aalto University</li> </ul>	Fall 2022
Network Security, Aalto University	Fall 2022
<ul> <li>Formal Languages and Finite Automata, University of Leeds</li> </ul>	Spring 2020